<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tvvo famous sea-fights. Lately made, betwixt the fleetes of the King of Spaine, and the fleetes of the Hollanders The one, in the West-Indyes: the other, the eight of this present moneth of February, betwixt Callis and Gravelin. In the former, the Hollander suffered. In the latter the Spaniard lost. Two relations not vnfit for these times to animate noble spirits to attempt and accomplish brave actions.</title>
            <title>Relacion verdadera, de la gran vitoria que han alcançado en el Brasil la gente de la Baia de Todos Santos, contra los Olandeses. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11833</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22132</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117010</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852225</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852225</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17537</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11833)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17537)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1155:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tvvo famous sea-fights. Lately made, betwixt the fleetes of the King of Spaine, and the fleetes of the Hollanders The one, in the West-Indyes: the other, the eight of this present moneth of February, betwixt Callis and Gravelin. In the former, the Hollander suffered. In the latter the Spaniard lost. Two relations not vnfit for these times to animate noble spirits to attempt and accomplish brave actions.</title>
                  <title>Relacion verdadera, de la gran vitoria que han alcançado en el Brasil la gente de la Baia de Todos Santos, contra los Olandeses. English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Bernard Alsop and Thomas Fawcet] for Nath: Butter and Nic: Bourne, with priviledge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1639.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first relation is a translation of: Relacion verdadera, de la gran vitoria que han alcançado en el Brasil la gente de la Baia de Todos Santos contra los Olandeses.</note>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A relation of two famous sea-fights.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Naval battles --  West Indies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Naval battles --  Netherlands --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17537:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TVVO FAMOVS SEA-FIGHTS. Lately made, Betwixt the Fleetes of the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and the Fleetes of the <hi>Hollanders,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The one, in the <hi>West-Indyes:</hi> The other, The Eight of this preſent Moneth of <hi>February,</hi> betwixt <hi>Callis</hi> and <hi>Gravelin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the former, <hi>the</hi> Hollander <hi>ſuffered.</hi> In the latter, <hi>the</hi> Spaniard <hi>lost.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two Relations not vnfit for theſe Times, to animate Noble Spirits to attempt and accompliſh brave Actions.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for NATH: BVTTER and NIC: BOVRNE, with Priviledge. 1639.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:17537:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17537:2"/>
            <head>A TRVE RELATION of the voyage of the <hi>Galleons</hi> and of the two Battailes they had with the <hi>Hollanders</hi> above <hi>Pan de Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nana<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nas,</hi> this yeare in <hi>September,</hi> 1638.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>On Carlos de Ybarra</hi> with the Navie of Guarde of the <hi>Indies</hi> which he governeth, ſet forth from <hi>Cadiz</hi> the 29 of <hi>Aprill</hi> this yeare 1638. with fewer Sea-men and men of Warre then hee had done former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, having remained in <hi>Spaine</hi> with ſeaven Galle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to carry his Majeſties Plate in them, and the Plate of particular men.</p>
            <p>Hee arrived at <hi>Cartagena</hi> the 12 of <hi>Iune,</hi> and the 21 of the ſame, he ſet forth towards <hi>Puerto Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo,</hi> where he arrived the 29 of the foreſaid moneth.</p>
            <p>On the 15 of <hi>Iuly</hi> hee ſet foorth from that Port with the ſaid Plate. He arrived at <hi>Cartagena</hi> on the firſt of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> amidſt calmes and contrary windes.</p>
            <p>There opening his Commiſſion hee found a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, which his Majeſty had ſent unto him from
<pb facs="tcp:17537:3"/>
               <hi>Spaine,</hi> together with a Letter under his Royall hand, dated the 28 of <hi>May</hi> of the ſaid yeare, and Signed by <hi>Don Fernando Ruiz de Contreras,</hi> in which he advertiſed him; That there were ſet forth from <hi>Holland</hi> tenne tall Ships, with direction, that they ſhould leave in <hi>Braſill,</hi> men and Munition, and paſſe to the coaſts of <hi>Terra Firma</hi> and <hi>Havana,</hi> to meet with this Navie, and that there would bee joyned with the ſaid Navie of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> 14 Ships, which were already upon thoſe coaſts of <hi>Terra Firma</hi> and <hi>Havana,</hi> and theſe forces being ſo much ſuperiour to thoſe, which the ſaid <hi>Don Carlos</hi> went withall, his Majeſty charged him deeply, that hee ſhould have a care to diſpoſe the matter ſo, that the Enemy might not meet him, and that if hee did, he might find that reſiſtance and valour, which might be expected: And that conſidering the ſmall For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which <hi>Don Carlos</hi> had on his ſide, hee had or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, that foure <hi>Veſſels</hi> ſhould bee made ready to come to his ayde; alſo charging him, to apply con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient meanes to free this Treaſure from the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and that hee ſhould be carefull in like manner, concerning that which came from <hi>New Spaine,</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king care of both buſineſſes according to the hope conceived of his prudence and valour; and that he ſhould conſider, how fit it was, hee ſhould returne into <hi>Spaine</hi> this yeare, in regard of the neceſſity there was of this Treaſure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Don Carlos</hi> having ſeene both the Direction and Letter, commanded all the places of the Souldiers throughout the Army to be ſetled ſo farre as might be, for he wanted many men, and to prepare the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb facs="tcp:17537:3"/>Galleons the beſt he might, giving neceſſary di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections for battaile, aſſigning withall the ſtanding which each one was to hold.</p>
            <p>Hee departed from <hi>Cartagena</hi> on the 7 of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt,</hi> towards the Port of <hi>Havana</hi> (a reſolution few would have undertaken) holding it for certaine, that he was to meet with the enemy, who was ſo ſtrong. It was only the zeale, with which he ſerveth his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and the avoyding of winterings, as hee hath done theſe yeares paſt, in which hee hath governed this Navie.</p>
            <p>On the 23 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> hee arrived at the <hi>Cape de Corrientos,</hi> where he found Letters of the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Havana,</hi> written eleven dayes before, in which he affirmed, that there were not above ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or eight Ships, which ſayled in that coaſt, vpon the 26 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> he arrived at <hi>Pan de Cana<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nas,</hi> which is twelve Leagues from <hi>Havana;</hi> and on the 30 of the ſaid Moneth, riding above the ſaid <hi>Pan de Cana<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi> by reaſon the weather was contrary to the going to <hi>Havana<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> There were diſcovered that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſeaventeene ſayles, which went towards the Land, &amp; the day following being the 31 of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid month, there was diſcovered in the morning the Navie of the Enemy, which made towards this of ours. Then <hi>Don Carlos</hi> ſet vp the Royall ſtandard, and diſcharged a peece, which was a ſignall of Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile, that every one might take his place; and that the Pinaſſe <hi>De la Margarita,</hi> might doe the ſame, which had met him at the Cape <hi>de Corrientos;</hi> and with top ſayle, and foreſayle, and with ſayle of bolt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſprite extended at length, he went towards the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,
<pb facs="tcp:17537:4"/>who diſpoſed his Navie in forme following.</p>
            <p>The Admirall, and three others of the greateſt Ships, amongſt which one great one bore a ſtreamer came vpon our Admirall. The Vice-admirall, and other two Ships came againſt the Vice-admirall of our Navie, and the other Ships againſt the reſt of our Galleons. The enemies Admirall lay aboord ours, putting his boltſprite through the fore-maſt, ſhee had many men hidden aloft, a thing which hath not beene ſeene in a <hi>Holland</hi> Ship, ſhee lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boord of vs two houres having taken the wind, with reſolution to put forth men into our Ship. She had three tyres of Artillery, two principall, and thoſe of the fore-caſtle, which in all were 54 Pieces. The weight of the Bullets was fifty, and 25, and 20 pounds: this is notorious by many bullets of theſe kinds, ſhot by the Enemy, which are now heaped together in this our Admirall. Shee gaue three ſhots with her Artillery, and many with her Muskets; and in the interim the other three Ships, which came with her, ſtood diſcharging their Artillery from their ſides, and poope at our Admirall. <hi>Don Carlos</hi> had then given order, that no Musket, nor Artillery ſhould be diſcharged, till hee ſhould give notice. He gaue notice, when the Enemies Admirall came to boord him; the Artillery was diſcharged thrice, and many times the Musketiers, which was diſpoſed in good order. The enemy received ſo much hurt hereby, that cutting of ropes and other preparations he diſaboorded vs, and fled, and <hi>Don Carlos</hi> purſued him, ſo farre as was ſufficient, that this might be underſtood. The enemy ſet our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall
<pb facs="tcp:17537:4"/>on fire fiue times, and ſtill it was quenched; ſhee received a great number of ſhot both below, and above, ſixe and twenty perſons were ſlaine, and fifty hurt, and amongſt the reſt <hi>Don Carlos</hi> himſelfe, who going about to take a ball of Wild-fire, which they had caſt ſecretly at his feet, it broke and woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him in the face, arme, and thigh, and yet for all this, he left not his place, giving neceſſary directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for that which was in hand, the wounds not being of ſuch confideration, as to make him for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare ſtanding on his feet. Amongſt thoſe that were wounded, and ſlaine, there were perſons of much e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme. The Captaine of the Sea, and Warre, and the Gentlemen paſſengers, and comerades of <hi>Don Carlos</hi> deſerved much that day, for the valour which they ſhewed. The Viceadmirall of this our Armada was boorded with the Viceadmirall of the enemy, figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with her, and other two ſhips, and in freeing her ſelfe from her, the Viceadmirall of the Enemy came to our Admirall on the lee-ſide, and gaue her a great ſhot which was anſwered with another. The Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admirall of this our Nauy, loſt the ſayle of her bolt ſprite, and the yard of her fore-maſt, and had a fire kindled in her, which was hard to quench; In all <hi>Don Pedro de Vſua</hi> ſhewed well his valour, who was wounded. From the Galleon in which was <hi>Sancho de Vrdanivia,</hi> who without direction put 2 ſtreamers on his top, whereby he gaue occaſion to the enemy to ſhoote at her with greater care, they tooke away the boltſprit at one ſhot. The other Galleons of this our Armada ſtood fighting with thoſe of the enemy with ſuch valor, as may be conceived of ſuch Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines,
<pb facs="tcp:17537:5"/>as thoſe were, which commanded them.</p>
            <p>This fight continued more then eight houres, and in the evening the nauy of the enemy united it ſelfe, the Admirall taking downe the Standard, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging a Piece, and having ſtood croſſe to our Armada above the winde more then an houre, they tooke reſolution to flye, ſpreading all their ſayles, and we followed them; not being able to goe to <hi>la Havana</hi> becauſe the winde was contrary, wee went making ſeverall bounds, now this, now that way from <hi>Pan de Cana<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nas</hi> to <hi>Las Meſas de Muriel,</hi> untill the third of <hi>September,</hi> when the enemy was diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the morning, and came in the ſame order with 13 ſhips to fight again with this our Armada, which defended it ſelf with the ſame reſolution, as before, the Admirall of the enemy came to encounter with this our Armada; ſhe had no men above covered o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, but they were apparelled in white canvas, ſhee gaue two ſhots of Artillery, and was anſwered with other two, and we followed her, untill we were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to turne to ſeeke out <hi>Sancho de Vrdanivia,</hi> who had ſtayed longer behind then all the reſt, whereby the greater number of the enemies ſhips paſſing by him, they ſtood ſhooting at him, ſo that this our Admirall was forced to come vp to him, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhips of the enemy ſtood diſcharging at ours, and ours at theirs without boording any.</p>
            <p>There was wounded in this encounter <hi>Don Pablos. de Contreras,</hi> who was Captaine of one of the ſeaven Galleons; and Captaine <hi>Facinto Melendos,</hi> who was Commander of another, and hee ſent mee word, that in this Shippe there were ſlayne,
<pb facs="tcp:17537:5"/>and wounded more than thirty. This encounter continued more than eight houres; there were in this our Admirall 26. perſons wounded, and ſlaine; and amongſt them ſome of ſpeciall note. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to ſpeake with <hi>Sancho</hi> de <hi>Vrdanivia,</hi> hee ſaid, that his Galleon had a great leake, and his maſtes were torne with ſhot, and that hee was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furniſhed. Don <hi>Carlos</hi> took preſently into his Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leon the plate which he carried of his Majeſties, &amp; of other particular men, and ſent him men, from his Admirall, &amp; gave direction to the Marqueſe de <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deronſa,</hi> and to the Admirals Lievetenant <hi>Ivan</hi> de <hi>Campos,</hi> that each of them ſhould ſend him men out of their ſhips; and preſently the day follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the morning, <hi>Sancho</hi> de <hi>Vrdanivia</hi> ſent a note to Don <hi>Carlos,</hi> ſignifying unto him, that his maſts and yards were torne with ſhot, and that by no meanes hee could ſayle, and that in the firſt and ſecond time of his fight, there were ſlaine and wounded more than thirty perſons; and that wee were over againſt the Port de <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nannas;</hi> and that his Pilot told him, that hee could put him in there, it being a ſhip of ſmall burthen, and would ſave the artillery, cheſts of Indico, and other things which hee carried. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently there was a peece of Ordinance diſcharged, and a Flagge of Counſell ſet up, whereupon all aſſembled, and hearing the Pilot ſpeake, they agreed that hee ſhould goe to the Port, and there ſhould ſave all that hee could. And <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho</hi> de <hi>Vrdanivia</hi> being departed to performe
<pb facs="tcp:17537:6"/>that which was determined; the Admirals Lieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant <hi>Ivan</hi> de <hi>Campos,</hi> Don <hi>Gaſpar</hi> de <hi>Garaca</hi> Captaine of ſea and warre of this our Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and others of the Aſſembly, ſaid, that it was convenient, that this Armada ſhould goe to Nova Eſpania, and the caſe ſeeming ſo farre different from that which Don <hi>Carlos</hi> was char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged withall, which was to goe to the <hi>Havana;</hi> oppoſing this conceit, they anſwered all with out-cries, that hee ſhould not take upon his ſhoulders ſo heavy a burthen; yeelding reaſons as afterwards ſhall bee ſaid, ſo much in favour of his Majeſtie, and of the good of the Commence. Don <hi>Carlos</hi> tooke reſolution to goe forth of the Admirall, and take with him the whole Aſſembly into the Galleon of Don <hi>Pablos</hi> de <hi>Contreras,</hi> where was, and came embarked Don <hi>Ivan</hi> de <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravajal,</hi> of the Royall Counſell of his Majeſty for the Indies, and Generall Viſitor of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diences of <hi>Linia,</hi> and of <hi>Las Charcas,</hi> and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving heard the one and the other, his vote ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in writing was, that it was very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for the ſervice of his Majeſtie to goe to Nova Eſpania; becauſe thereby they ſhould ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure his Plate, and the Plate of private perſons; that the wind was contrary for <hi>Havana,</hi> and faire for Noua Eſpania; that the change of the Moone would bee within three dayes, and that thoſe ſeaſons of September had been alwaies evill upon thoſe Coſts; that any of the ſix Galleons which remained, ſeparating herſelfe, the enemy would
<pb facs="tcp:17537:6"/>take her, that our forces were ſmall, thoſe of the enemie grew greater, ſeeing beſides thoſe, which they had in their Navie, with which they had given battaile twice, they expected foure ſhips more, which went to joyne with them, and that they were to conſider the want of the ſhip of <hi>Sancho</hi> de <hi>Vrdanivia:</hi> and the reſt of the Captaines, who were preſent, declared, that they had ſpent halfe their bullets and powder, with which they departed from Spaine; and that they conceived that the Enemy would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne once, yea many times to fight with our ſaid Armada; and that in fighting two or three times, there would bee left neither bullets for the artillerie, nor powder; a dammage ſo well knowne, and unremediable: and that there might bee feared ſome bad ſucceſſe to all this Armada, or to a part of it; and that their wintering would be certaine in <hi>Havana,</hi> becauſe they were to enter into it late, and could not departe, by reaſon they were to repaire the ſhips, which for the moſt part had beene ill handled; and that the enemie, would not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the mouth of the Port, till the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter were farre gone on; and that it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to make this Winter in Nova Eſpania, where all was ſecured, and the Fleet of Nova Eſpania, was thought for certain not to have departed, becauſe it was conceived that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie had ſent thither the ſame direction, which hee had done to Don <hi>Carlos;</hi> and that there
<pb facs="tcp:17537:7"/>the ſhips might bee repaired, and furniſhed with proviſion, powder, and bullets. Many other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were alledged, which although they ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med very ſtrong, and convenient to Don <hi>Carlos,</hi> &amp; Don <hi>Pedro,</hi> de <hi>Vſna,</hi> nevertheleſſe they were of opinion they ſhould incite the enemy on the way to Havana. Yet Don <hi>Pedro</hi> de <hi>Vſna</hi> being come to his ſhip, and having ſeene the foure ſhips, which were joyned to the enemie, and other three, which appeared from the top, and went in like manner to joyne themſelves with the ſaid Navie, which conſiſted in all of twenty foure ſhips; hee ſent a meſſage by Don <hi>Diego</hi> de <hi>Gues</hi> Captaine of ſea and war, and of the Vice-admirall, unto Don <hi>Carlos,</hi> telling him, that accidents did change the condition of buſineſſes, and ſeeing the forces of the enemie were ſo great, and ours ſo ſmall, it ſeemed good to him to follow the common adviſe of all; and Don <hi>Carlos</hi> agreed thereunto, and gave neceſſary directions for each one to hold their courſe for Nova Eſpania, the Galleon of <hi>Sancho</hi> de <hi>Vrdanivia</hi> remaining in the ſaid Port <hi>de Canannas</hi> in the ſight of this our Armado, unſeene by the Navy of the enemie, which remained as it ſeemed to all with much hurt and loſſe of men. And the next day being the fifth of this preſent moneth in the evening, the enemies Navie appeared, conſiſting of 24. ſhips, and ſtood in the wind of this our Armado, and that night the lanternes had lights ſet up in them in our Admirall, and Vice-admirall,
<pb facs="tcp:17537:7"/>that the enemie, if he deſired to returne to fight, with this our Armado, might know where we were; and the next day following in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning they appeared not, nor were they ſeene any more. Our voyage was ſecure, and on Friday, being the foure and twentieth of September, we arrived at the Port of Saint <hi>Ivan</hi> de Lua, where wee found the Fleet of Nova Eſpania, her Generall Don <hi>Martin</hi> de <hi>Vrbea,</hi> with generall content one of another for having performed ſo great a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice for his Majeſtie; for both the Armado and and Fleet were joyned together, and the Plate alſo of both Kingdomes, belonging to his Majeſty, and particular men; the enemy likewiſe ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with loſſe. From this place wee indeavour to depart the ſooneſt wee may, making ready the ſhips, as well thoſe of the Fleet, as the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leons. His Majeſty is informed of all by two ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſments duplicated; to the end he may order and command what ſhall pleaſe him; for from this time unto the ſetting forth of this Armado, there will bee ſpace to anſwer to theſe two adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements, and in caſe no other direction come, Don <hi>Carlos</hi> will go on in the purſuit of his voyage, with the Armado and Fleet for Spaine.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>With Licence in <hi>Sevil</hi> by <hi>Nicolas Rodriguez,</hi> in the ſtreet of <hi>Genua,</hi> 
                  <date>this yeare <hi>1638.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="abstract">
            <pb facs="tcp:17537:8"/>
            <head>An Abſtract of the Spaniſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, wherein their owne loſſe is ſpecified; and the Dutch but pointed at in generall.</head>
            <list>
               <item>The Spaniſh Infantry, which were ſlaine amounted to <hi>34.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Infantry hurt to <hi>77.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Seamen ſlaine to <hi>18.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Seamen hurt to <hi>34.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Paſſengers ſlaine to <hi>13.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The paſſengers wounded to <hi>17.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:17537:8"/>
            <head>A ſharp add bloody Sea-fight, betwixt the Hollanders and Dunkerkers: Feb. <hi>8. 18. 1639.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The 18. of this month, halfe an houre after Sun riſing, the Fleet of the King of Spaine; conſiſting of 10. great ſhips of warre, 4. great Fregats, 5. great ſhips of burden, and one Pinace, laden with Souldiers, came out of the Channell of the Fort of Mardike into the Sea, with intention to ſet upon and fight with our Fleet, conſiſting of 10. great Veſſels and two Fregats. At 9. a clocke in the morning we began the fight, mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ourſelves with the enemy, who with divers of their ſhips came upon us. The fight having du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red till 3. of clocke and halfe in the afternoone the Enemy betooke himſelfe to flight returning under the ſaid Fort, except 7. of the ſaid great ſhips furniſhed for warre, which were conſtrained to run themſelves a ground, to ſhun ſinking. Our leakes were ſo great, that we were continually em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in pumping and ſtopping them: wherupon ſix of them came of again, but the Vice-admirall of Dunkerk ſorer battered than the reſt, ſtuck faſt ſtil, the enemy ſetting her on fire, for feare we ſhould gaine her ordinance and furniture, ſhe being a new ſhip and never at ſea before. We became maſters of two ſhips like the Vice-admirall, which were not of thoſe 7. and were furniſhed each with two
<pb facs="tcp:17537:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>hundred and thirty or forty men, 16. peeces of braſſe canon, and forty of iron. And becauſe our ſhips were much battered, and mine eſpecially, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all rent and torne, and having 70 of her men ſlaine or wounded, we were faine to returne home to mend our ſhips and make them fit to returne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain with the firſt. I may not forget to tell you that among the Souldiers which the enemy had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board, were the beſt old Wallon Regiments, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of 2000. men in 20. Companies, appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to bee landed at the Groyne. This is what I can ſay of this particular being now ſayling homewards.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
